Set Phrases, a Cultural Indoctrination to American Norms When I learned the alphabet
as a child, I heard it before I saw it. I heard that the last four letters were W,
X, Y, Z. I thought that W was a long, strange name for a letter, but I didn't
question it any more than I did H. It was just a name. Many years later, it struck
me that it was a double U. Of course, a W is really UU. Funny feeling, though, when
I realized that something I had taken for granted for so many years had a background
meaning that I had completely overlooked. This funny feeling is exactly what most
native speakers get when a two-word phrase is stressed on the wrong word. When two
individual words go through the cultural process of becoming a set phrase, the
original sense of each word is more or less forgotten and the new meaning
completely takes over. When we hear the word painkiller, we think anesthetic. If,
however, someone says painkiller, it brings up the strength and almost
unrelated meaning of kill. When you have a two-word phrase, you have to put stress on
either the first word or the second word. If you stress both or neither, it's not
clear what you are trying to say. Stress on the first word is more noticeable and
one of the most important concepts of that you are going to study. At first glance,
it doesn't seem significant, but the more you look at this concept, the more you are
going to realize that it reflects how we Americans think, what concepts we have
adopted as our own, and what things we consider important. Set phrases are our
cultural icons or word images. They are indicators of a determined use that we
have internalized. These set phrases, with stress on the first word, have been taken
into everyday English from descriptive phrases with stress on the second word. As
soon as a descriptive phrase becomes a set phrase, the emphasis shifts from the
second word to the first. The original sense of each word is more or less
forgotten and the new meaning takes over. Set phrases indicate that we have
internalized this phrase as an image, that we all agree on a concrete idea that this
phrase represents. A hundred years or so ago, when Levi Strauss first came out with
his denim pants, they were described as blue jeans. We all agree on the image,
however, they are blue jeans. A more recent example would be the descriptive
phrase, he's a real party animal. This slang expression refers to someone who has
a great time at a party. When it first became popular, the people using it needed
to explain with their intonation that he was an animal at a party. As time passed,
the expression became cliche and we changed the intonation to, he's a real
party animal because everyone knew what it meant. Clichés are hard to recognize in a
new language because what may be an old and tired expression to a native speaker
may be fresh and exciting to a newcomer. One way to look at English from the inside
out, rather than always looking from the outside in, is to get a feel for what
Americans have already accepted and internalized. This starts out as a purely
language phenomenon, but you will notice that as you progress and undergo the
relentless cultural indoctrination of standard intonation patterns, you will
find yourself expressing yourself with the language cues and signals that will mark
you as an insider, not an outsider. When the interpreter was translating for the
former Russian president Gorbachev about his trip to San Francisco in 1990, his
pronunciation was good, but he placed himself on the outside by repeatedly
saying, cable car. The phrase cable car is an image, an established entity, and was
very noticeable to hear it stressed on the second word as a mere description. An
important point that I would like to make is that the rules you are given here are
not meant to be memorized. This discussion is only an introduction to give you a
starting point in understanding and in recognizing what to listen for. Read it
over, think about it, then listen, try it out, listen some more, and try it out
again. As you become familiar with intonation, you will become more
comfortable with American norms, thus the cultural orientation or even cultural
indoctrination aspect of the following examples. Note, when you get the
impression that a two-word description could be hyphenated or even made into one
word, it's a signal that it could be a set phrase. For example, flashlight,
flash, light, flash, light. Also, stress the first word with street, main street,
and nationalities of food and people. Mexican food, Chinese girls.